Good morning track number three. Today is March 13th, it's 26th of
אדר. Adar. It's a beautiful snowy morning here in Riverdale. I'm Dan
Margulies filling in for Rabbi Linzer. We're going to pick up six
lines into נז עמוד א'. Nun Zayin Amud Aleph. You can see
thankfully today's דף daf is relatively short, just because תוספות Tosafot is
very long.
We don't think we'll get to the points in תוספות, Tosafot, I
want to make sure we explain the גמרא Gemara well.
But it's an interesting דף daf and it deals with the question
which we've already started to explore and part of the challenge of
our פרק perek here ambiguity is that very often we see the
word יין נסך Yayin Nesech being used and we're not sure whether
we're talking about יין נסך Yayin Nesech that's the דאורייתא De-Oraita prohibition
of wine that was used or or is leftover from being used
in idolatrous libations and whether it refers to the דרבנן De-Rabbanan rule
of סתם יינם, Stam Yeinam, any wine touched or handled by non-Jews
obviously with specific parameters. But the גמרא Gemara is very often going
to use the same term and equate them. We have to keep
track. At least in part because the major question
is:
is there a prohibition? We know that the יין נסך Yayin Nesech
that's actually been used for עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah is prohibited בהנאה.
be-hana'ah. There's a prohibition of deriving any financial, monetary, personal benefit from
it. And does that same איסור הנאה issur hana'ah apply to the
דרבנן De-Rabbanan prohibition of סתם יינם Stam Yeinam or not? That's going
to be a major debate in the ראשונים Rishonim as one of
the first topics that comes up in the שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch
and in the טור Tur about יין נסך. Yayin Nesech. But in
our סוגיא sugya this is sort of one of the one of
the main points that comes up today. So we're going to see
that today and we're also see sort of at what point for
certain הלכות halachot the rabbis created the דרבנן De-Rabbanan laws, how much
did they or did they not distinguish between adults and children and
things like that. Yeah, Michael, what's your— So
I know we're going to continue with this but this whole I
guess reluctance to פסק pasken like רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
is—so that was already established even in the time of the גמרא
Gemara it seems. You know, like because he's a דעת יחיד? da'at
yachid? You know, so it's like, oh, find another תנא tanna who'll
allow him? רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon was—was רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon like
a non-entity? I mean like— Well, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
is generally I mean in general across ש״ס Shas we try not
to פסק pasken like רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. We have rules against
it.
But that was even then? I'm asking about then.
Oh, oh, you're saying—
I
mean now, obviously, right?
No, I know, but same, but then they were reluctant to even
follow him. So like why?
Why? Because רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon he was outvoted, whatever.
I
mean obviously aren't these דרבננ׳ס De-Rabbanan's and yet we're still not פסק׳ינג
pasken'ing like רבי שמעון? Rabbi Shimon?
Yeah, because we still have rules of פסק psak and I mean
the general sense is still that רבי שמעון's Rabbi Shimon position represented
a minority position. Either he wasn't convincing to his colleagues at the
time or the traditions that he had received from רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva were different than what other rabbis had gotten from רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva or he was being more, you know, I don't know.
But we don't say ספק דרבנן לקולא safek De-Rabbanan l'kula and then
rely on רבי שמעון? Rabbi Shimon?
We don't do that. This is a general rule which is which
is important to emphasize, which is that when we talk about a
ספק safek of doubt, generally for the for the laws that are
being debated in the גמרא Gemara we don't consider a מחלוקת machlokes
to be a doubt for for the rules of ספק דרבנן, safek
De-Rabbanan, ספק דאורייתא לחומרא safek De-Oraita l'chumra things like that. Maybe one
exception came up earlier in the מסכת masechet like on דף ז׳.
daf zayin. There's in even in cases of debate around a דרבנן
De-Rabbanan maybe you should pick the more lenient position. But generally when
we're talking about a ספק safek we're talking about a doubtful case.
A doubt in the fact, not a doubtful פסק. psak. And usually
the sense is that the פסק psak was decided at some point.
Whether it was at the end of the תנא'יתיק Tanna'itic period, the
אמוראים Amora'im started coming up with rules of how to determine the
הלכה halacha from the תנאים. Tannaim. Certainly by the end of the
period of the אמוראים Amora'im and going into the, you know, post-
post-Talmudic era, there developed relatively well-established rules for how to extract the
final פסק psak from the גמרא. Gemara. And then all the debates
of the ראשונים Rishonim are about how exactly to apply those rules
in specific cases.
Okay, so the question we have today, we're going to have basically
a few different principles that we're going to get through as we
go.
So the גמרא Gemara says, ההוא עובדא דהוה בבירם. Hahu uvda de-hava
be-Biram. There was a certain case in בירם. Biram. בירם Biram is
some city.
We're starting six lines down on נז עמוד א'. Nun Zayin Amud
Aleph. ההוא עובדא דהוה בבירם. Hahu uvda de-hava be-Biram.
There was an incident in בירם. Biram. What happened? דההוא עובד כוכבים
דהוה קסליק בדיקלא. De-hahu oved kochavim de-hava kasalik be-dikla.
There was a non-Jew who was climbing up a palm tree. The
reason why they would climb the palm trees is to harvest the
dates. Now they use a cherry picker or a crane or something
but back then you had to actually climb the tree. ואייתי לולביה
בהדיה. V'aytei lulavei bahadei.
And he took down the לולב lulav from the top of the
tree as well or from the middle of the tree or something.
Imagine using the branch to poke the fruits, right? If you climb
the tree, you're standing in the middle of the tree but the
fruits are out on the side. You have to sever the fruits
from the branch, so you're going to poke it with something. So
he was poking it with this לולב. lulav. דהכא נחית De-haka nachit
נגע ברישיה דלולביה בחמרא naga be-reishei di-lulavei be-hamra שלא בכוונה. shelo b'kavana.
And at some point, whether he was coming down from the tree
or something like that, he nudged a flask of wine with the
end of the date branch. So he's holding a stick and he
pushed the jar of wine, and it was שלא בכוונה, shelo bekavana,
it was without intention.
He wasn't really planning or trying to do that. So that was
the question. This is the halachic question. Is there even a question?
Okay, maybe why is there even a question, but this was at
least the non-Jewish person contacted or moved the barrel of wine. So
שריא רב לזבוני לעובדי כוכבים. shari'ei Rav lizevunei le'ovdei kochavim.
Wouldn't it be allowed to be drunk?
Okay, so moving it in that regard is enough to have been
considered סתם יינם. stam yeinam. But what Rav—so what Rav—well we'll have
to parse Rav's פסק. psak. Rav said it's permissible to sell it
to non-Jews. So we could take that in two different ways. We
could interpret it the way Michael said, which is that oh, if
סתם יינם stam yeinam is prohibited בהנאה, behana'ah, then this is not
even סתם יינם. stam yeinam. This is totally permissible, but better not
to drink it anyway as some חומרא, chumra, and therefore sell it
to the non-Jews. Alternatively, we could understand it to be Rav thinks
that סתם יינם stam yeinam is מותר בהנאה, mutar behana'ah, you could
sell it but you're not allowed to drink it. And therefore the
solution in a case where it becomes סתם יינם stam yeinam is
to just sell it.
So based on this, I mean I don't know if you could
interpret this, so like this is a real question. Let's say there's
like a delivery truck driven by a non-Jew
with open bottles of wine.
Well, we don't know if there's an open bottle of wine.
Well it has to be an open bottle of wine. If it's
a closed bottle of wine it wouldn't make any sense.
Then somehow it nudged it but it didn't spill all
over. Out on a tree?
I'm not sure if the wine was at the top of the
tree or at the bottom of the tree. I think it makes
more sense if the wine was at the bottom of the tree
when he was coming down the tree and he had the stick
or whatever.
Anyway, but so I mean so if the non-Jew's like driving the
stuff and like
then—so driving in a truck is already maybe a different question. But
here the point—the question we have is if moving the wine שלא
בכוונה shelo bekavana without any intention is going to be considered, and
we're going to compare that to a case of a child moving
the wine or handling the wine.
But the truck is not moving.
I'm not sure a truck—driving a truck would count the same way.
But you can see the fact that he's not doing it with
his own hand, it's just something in between.
Right, so there is something in between but again—right. So we have
multiple pieces. He has no כוונה, kavana, he's holding a stick, not—not
touching it directly. And I mean those are the two main pieces
of why it would be more lenient. But again, holding a stick
and pushing something or nudging it is going to be basically equivalent.
The same reason why handling the bottle of wine is the same
as handling the wine itself, because you're—it's under your control, your action
determines the future of that wine.
One other question, you said about if it's a closed bottle it
doesn't matter?
If it's a closed bottle, right, or double—really we say double seal,
single seal, double seal, right, that's been discussed already a little bit,
it's going to come up more.
So those kinds of questions become obviously very important.
But so at what stage does the wine become safe that we
don't have to worry about it anymore? That's one of the main
questions in terms of wine production now is going to be how
much do Jewish people have to be involved in the production and
at what point does it become safe for the non-Jews to do
it? After the bottling, after it's been totally wrapped, once it's being
shipped off to the warehouse or you know those kind of questions.
Okay, so that was the case. So שריא רב לזבוני לעובדי כוכבים.
shari'ei Rav lizevunei le'ovdei kochavim. Rav said it's permissible to sell it
to non-Jews. So אמר ליה רב כהנא ורב אסי לרב. amar lei
Rav Kahana ve-Rav Assi le-Rav. Rav Kahana and Rav Assi said to
Rav, והא אמר הוא דאמר תינוק בן יומו הוא עושה יין נסך.
veha amar hu de'amar tinok ben yomo hu oseh yein nesech. Didn't
you, Rav, say that even a day-old baby who touches or moves
the wine makes it יין נסך, yein nesech, makes it סתם יינם?
stam yeinam? That is, even a child who has no דעת, da'at,
no כוונה, kavana, no control of their motion at all, is still
considered to be יין נסך yein nesech if a non-Jewish child touches
the wine. אמר להו אימר דאמרי אנא בשתייה בהנאה מי אמרי. amar
lehu eimar de'amri ana beshtiya behana'ah mi amri. So no, no, Rav
says, I distinguish between the permission to drink the wine and the
prohibition of איסור הנאה. issur hana'ah. That is, a non-Jewish baby or
non-Jewish child who touches the wine makes it סתם יינם stam yeinam
enough that it's prohibited to drink but not prohibited to derive benefit
from.
And the reason for that
is—the reason for that is it's a lower level piece of the
דין דרבנן. din derabbanan. And again, we still could parse it in
two different ways. We could say Rav thinks in general סתם יינם
stam yeinam is permissible בהנאה. behana'ah. That may be a bit of
a stretch but that's what some ראשונים Rishonim would understand. The other
is to say Rav thinks that this lower level סתם יינם stam
yeinam that's produced by a child or produced without כוונה, kavana, that
status is of a different status which is מותר בהנאה. mutar behana'ah.
And if it was done by a non-Jew with כוונה kavana to
be touching or handling the wine then it would still be אסור
בהנאה. assur behana'ah. So that's a different way to understand what Rav
is saying, but both of those come up here. So that so
far we just had there was a case, Rav gave a פסק,
psak, Rav's colleagues questioned him, and then he defended himself. He says
no, actually I distinguish between both the case of a child and
a case of an adult with no כוונה kavana that it's permissible
to derive benefit but it's prohibited to drink it.
They seemingly wanted to be more מחמיר. machmir. They said Rav, how
can you say— that this adult who touched the wine with a
lulav לולב, lulav, it's permissible to sell it? Didn't you say tinok
ben yomo oseh yayin nesech תינוק בן יומו עושה יין נסך? tinok
ben yomo oseh yayin nesech? So now we re-assess Rav's רב Rav's
statement. Gufa גופא. Gufa. Amar Rav אמר רב. Amar Rav. So Rav
רב, Rav, we're going back to what Rav רב Rav just taught.
Amar Rav אמר רב, Amar Rav, tinok ben yomo oseh yayin nesech
תינוק בן יומו עושה יין נסך. tinok ben yomo oseh yayin nesech.
So a child, even a day-old child, a non-Jewish child who handles
the wine creates yayin nesech יין נסך, yayin nesech, here really means
stam yeinam סתם יינם. stam yeinam. So eitivei איתיבי. eitivei. Rav Shimi
bar Hiyya רב שימי בר חייא Rav Shimi bar Hiyya leh-Rav ליה
לרב. leh-Rav. So Rav Shimi bar Hiyya רב שימי בר חייא Rav
Shimi bar Hiyya challenged Rav רב Rav from this braita ברייתא, braita,
this from the Tosefta תוספתא. Tosefta. Halokeach avadim min haovdei kochavim הלוקח
עבדים מן העובדי כוכבים. Halokeach avadim min haovdei kochavim. So we're going
to have two parts of the Tosefta תוספתא, Tosefta, the second part
is more relevant, but the first part is going to be brought
into conversation as well. The braita ברייתא braita says: Halokeach avadim min
haovdei kochavim הלוקח עבדים מן העובדי כוכבים, Halokeach avadim min haovdei kochavim,
a person who buys slaves from non-Jewish slave traders, shemalu velo tavlu
שמלו ולא טבלו. shemalu velo tavlu. They've undergone circumcision but they haven't
gone to the mikveh מקווה mikveh yet in for the purpose of
their having been converted to being slaves. That is, when a non-Jewish
man, let's say, is being bought as a slave by a Jewish
person, he has to undergo milah מילה milah and tvilah טבילה, tvilah,
and the milah מילה milah and tvilah טבילה tvilah are for the
sake of becoming an eved עבד. eved. And then when he's freed,
has to then undergo tvilah טבילה tvilah again for the purpose of
becoming a free person. Okay. Vekhen benei hashfachot shemalu velo tavlu וכן
בני השפחות שמלו ולא טבלו, Vekhen benei hashfachot shemalu velo tavlu, or
children born to shfachot שפחות, shfachot, that is, a Jewish person already
owns a female slave and she gives birth to these children, they
also, in a case where they had not gone to the mikveh
מקווה mikveh yet, they've only undergone their circumcision.
Rukan umidrasan bashuk tmei'ei רוקן ומדרסן בשוק טמאי. Rukan umidrasan bashuk tmei'ei.
We have to parse this. There are two halachot הלכות halachot that
are being taught here. Number one is that mideoraita מדאורייתא mideoraita non-Jews
cannot become tamei טמא tamei and cannot make other things tamei טמא.
tamei. But there is a din derabbanan דין דרבנן din derabbanan that
all non-Jews are considered to be zav זב zav and zavah זבה
zavah miderabbanan מדרבנן. miderabbanan.
So we treat their, so that means rukan רוקן, rukan, the spit,
the only tamei טמא tamei person whose bodily fluids like spit, urine,
etc. are tamei טמא tamei is someone of the level of a
zav זב zav or a zavah זבה, zavah, and also midras מדרס,
midras, if they sit on a chair, if they sit on a
bench, if they ride a horse, all of the things underneath them,
even like Princess and the Pea, even if there are, you know,
a thousand mattresses or whatever, all of them become tamei טמא tamei
all the way down. That's called midras מדרס. midras. And both of
those are dinim דינים dinim that apply specifically to the rank of
zav זב zav and zavah זבה, zavah, those level of tumah טומאה,
tumah, more or less.
And therefore, why bashuk בשוק bashuk though?
So what is bashuk בשוק? bashuk? That's the second halacha הלכה halacha
that's being recorded here.
Because usually I think about like sfeka detumah bereshut
hayachid ספק טומאה ברשות היחיד. sfeka detumah bereshut hayachid. Okay, so we
have two rules that we learn already back in Masechet Sotah מסכת
סוטה, Masechet Sotah, which is that number one, when we have a
case of tumah טומאה tumah that's found, a case of safek tumah
ספק טומאה. safek tumah. Usually our rules for safek ספק, safek, as
Michael brought up already, are we say safek derabbanan lekula vesafek deoraita
lechumra ספק דרבנן לקולא וספק דאורייתא לחומרא, safek derabbanan lekula vesafek deoraita
lechumra, that rabbinic laws we treat leniently and biblical laws we treat
stringently. But there's another set of rules which applies to rules of
tumah טומאה, tumah, which immeshes with that in a different way, which
is, when we find a doubtful case of tumah טומאה, tumah, safek
tumah bereshut hayachid ספק טומאה ברשות היחיד, safek tumah bereshut hayachid, if
it's in a private place, which generally here is not taken to
mean the rules for Shabbat שבת, Shabbat, but if there are fewer
than three people gathered together, it's in a private area, that level
of tumah טומאה, tumah, if it's safek bereshut hayachid ספק ברשות היחיד,
safek bereshut hayachid, it's still considered tamei טמא. tamei. But if it's
found bereshut harabim ברשות הרבים, bereshut harabim, in a public area where
there are three-plus people, that could even be in a building or
in a house, but there are many people gathered there, then safek
tumah bereshut harabim sfeko tahor ספק טומאה ברשות הרבים ספקו טהור. safek
tumah bereshut harabim sfeko tahor. We treat the doubtful case as if
it's tahor טהור. tahor. So what we said here now is
rukan umidrasan bashuk tamei רוקן ומדרסן בשוק טמא. rukan umidrasan bashuk tamei.
So it sounds like bashuk tamei בשוק טמא, bashuk tamei, in public,
right, bashuk בשוק bashuk is in public, so it sounds like we
actually treat this level of tumah טומאה tumah that's applied to these
non-Jewish avadim עבדים avadim who have not fully become Jewish avadim עבדים,
avadim, right, they still haven't gone to the mikveh מקווה, mikveh, are
being treated with their derabbanan tumah דרבנן טומאה, derabbanan tumah, right, in
a very strict way, because we treat even safek bereshut harabim ספק
ברשות הרבים, safek bereshut harabim, we treat it as tamei טמא. tamei.
Or it's not said here safek ספק, safek, but I think that's
what's being implied by the categorization by the use of the word
shuk שוק. shuk. But again, we could say, oh, maybe it only
means bashuk tamei בשוק טמא bashuk tamei if it's bevada-i בוודאי, bevada-i,
but then why would the word shuk שוק shuk matter at all?
So it takes some parsing, we'll come back to it. Okay, and
the second half, ve'amri lah tahor ואמרי לה טהור, ve'amri lah tahor,
so some people teach this same braita ברייתא braita but with the
word tahor טהור, tahor, which would make more sense, that is, okay,
we treat them as if it's a case of safek ספק safek
or it's a case of this derabbanan tumah דרבנן טומאה, derabbanan tumah,
we're more lenient about it bashuk בשוק. bashuk. So there are two
extremes. We could either say we treat the vada-i וודאי vada-i as
tahor טהור, tahor, which is more lenient than usual because it's only
a derabbanan tumah דרבנן טומאה derabbanan tumah and they were more lenient
about it, or we treat it even as safek ספק safek is
tamei טמא, tamei, and that's actually more stringent than even deoraita tumah
דאורייתא טומאה. deoraita tumah. So those are two different ways to read
this braita ברייתא, braita, both are interesting. And then the second half
of the braita ברייתא, braita, yeinam יינם, yeinam, the wine that_ Handled
by these slaves who haven't fully converted, גדולים עושים יין נסך, gedolim
osim yayin nesech, if they are adults, it becomes יין נסך, yayin
nesech, קטנים אין עושים יין נסך. ketanim ein osim yayin nesech. It
sounds like from this ברייתא, braita, contradiction for רב. Rav. Because it
sounds like even children, slave children who handle the wine, and these
are slaves who haven't fully converted to Judaism. Right,
that's the point. Even a non-Jewish child is still nonetheless creates יין
נסך. yayin nesech. So that's a proof against רב. Rav. רב Rav
says תינוק
בן יומו עושה יין
נסך.
tinok ben yomo
ose yayin nesech. Oh, sorry, I read it backwards. Oops. This ברייתא
braita says אין עושים יין נסך, ein osim yayin nesech, that it
doesn't, so it is a proof against רב. Rav. Because רב Rav
says that children can make יין נסך yayin nesech and this ברייתא
braita says that they do not. Okay.
Right. But what I would say is you can distinguish. I mean,
you know, the reason why they don't make it is because they're
somewhere along the way,
they're somewhere along the line to becoming Jewish. You could say something
like that.
גדולים gedolim versus קטנים ketanim indicates that the distinction is about age,
not about status. That's true.
So let's see here. So אלו הן גדולים ואלו הן קטנים. eilu
hen gedolim ve-eilu hen ketanim. So what, why is there this distinction
between גדולים gedolim and קטנים? ketanim? So גדולים יודעים בטיב עבודה כוכבים
ומשמשיה gedolim yodim be-tiv avoda kochavim u-meshamesheha because adults know the practices
of their עבודה זרה. avoda zara. So we're concerned, at least, if
and again this is coming back to what's actually the motivation of
the דרבנן de-rabbanan סתם יינם, stam yeinam, is it because we're concerned
even about a risk of עבודה זרה, avoda zara, or is it
because of some other reason, because of חתנות chatnut or something like
that. So here, it sounds like it's about the technicalities of the
עבודה זרה. avoda zara. Only the adults actually know how to worship
עבודה זרה. avoda zara. The children don't know all the details.
Even back then, they were giving them bad חינוך.
chinuch. Oh, bad, right, the עבודה זרה avoda zara religion doesn't have
the same requirements of חינוך chinuch as we do, maybe. But again,
we don't trust children to be able to do מצוות mitzvot for
us either. So maybe it's because they're not fully educated along the
way. So גדולים יודעים בטיב עבודה כוכבים ומשמשיה, gedolim yodim be-tiv avoda
kochavim u-meshamesheha, they know all the rules and therefore we're more concerned
that they're going to make יין נסך. yayin nesech. קטנים אינם יודעים
בטיב עבודה כוכבים ומשמשיה. ketanim einam yodim be-tiv avoda kochavim u-meshamesheha. So
the children don't know and therefore we're not concerned that they're going
to make יין נסך. yayin nesech. So that would be why this
ברייתא braita is teaching a more lenient position for children, seemingly contradiction
to רב. Rav. So קטני היא הא גדולים אין קטנים לא. ketani
hi ha gedolim in ketanim lo. So it sounds from this, or
we can infer from this fully, that only adults can make a
יין נסך yayin nesech and not children. So how can רב Rav
defend himself? So רב Rav has to say תרגמה אבני שפחות. targema
abnei shefachot. רב Rav said it's speaking specifically about בני שפחות, bnei
shefachot, those who are the children of women who have already been
made fully שפחה כנענית, shifcha kena'anit, a non-Jewish slave owned by a
Jewish master. So in that regard, then it's less of a חידוש.
chiddush. So look what רש"י Rashi says. אף על פי שנולדו בבית
ישראל ולא גדלו בין עובדי כוכבים בעו מילה וטבילה. af al pi
she-noldu be-veit yisrael ve-lo gadlu bein ovedei kochavim bau mila u-tvilah. That
is, they've grown up in a Jewish household. Their mother is owned
by a Jewish slave master. So these children, even though so they
on a technicality have not undergone מילה mila and טבילה tvila to
make them of the status of עבד כנעני eved kena'ani in the
fullest sense that their handling of the wine would not make it
יין נסך. yayin nesech. וכשלא טבלה אמו מתחילה קמיירי דלא טבלה אמו
אינהו למה להו טבילה. ukshelo tavla imo mi-techila ka-mairei de-lo tavla imo
inhu lama lehu tvila. So the point is what רב Rav would
understand this as saying, ah, בני שפחות bnei shefachot have a lower
level requirement at the, they still need to go to מקוה, mikvah,
they still need the מילה, mila, but because they've grown up in
a Jewish household, we could even presume a higher level of surety
that the children do not have any familiarity with עבודה זרה avoda
zara and that therefore they're not going to have any risk of
making it real יין נסך. yayin nesech. And then therefore the דרבנן
de-rabbanan of סתם יינם stam yeinam will not apply to them.
But if they're older and still grew up in a Jewish household,
we are worried about it.
So at some point you have to have a cutoff and say
okay, they got it from somewhere or they, meaning the slave master
also has an obligation to do מילה mila and טבילה tvila for
them.
But
where it's not, it's like growing up in a house without a
TV and then going to your aunt's and uncle's who do have
a TV. So as long as they're in the controlled environment of
the Jew's home, then they're not familiar with עבודה זרה. avoda zara.
But as they grow up, it makes sense that external exposures kick
in.
Right. So but then the problem for רב Rav is וכן כי
אמר רוקן ומדרסן. ve-chen ki amar rukan u-midrasan. So רב Rav will
interpret it similarly regarding the first half of the ברייתא braita about
the spit and the מדרס midras of these non-Jewish slaves. That is,
they still retain the status, so that could also explain why and
again for the איכא דאמרי ika de-amrei that it was טהור, tahor,
it makes a lot of sense because רב's Rav teaching now is
like oh, we could be more lenient for them regarding they grew
up in the, no, or I'm not sure exactly. וכן כי אמר
רוקן ומדרסן ve-chen ki amar rukan u-midrasan that fine,
now the opposite, that we should still treat them as טמא tamei
because they're still not Jewish, they still need מילה mila and טבילה.
tvila. So at a technical level for things like טומאה tumah and
whatever, we're still going to treat them that way. But for something
which has a clear reason... סתם יינם stam yeinam we’re going to
relax the standard. So הניחא למאן דאמר טמא. hanicha leman d’amar tamei.
That makes sense according to the reading of the ברייתא braita that
reads it as טמא. tamei. אלא למאן דאמר טהור מאי איכא למימר.
ela leman d’amar tahor mai ika lemimar. How can we understand the
ברייתא, braita, the version of the ברייתא braita that says טהור tahor
according to רב’s Rav interpretation that it applies specifically to the בני
שפחות? benei shefachot? So
הא קמשמע לן עבדים דומייא דבני שפחות, ha kamashma lan avadim dumya
dibnei shefachot, it must apply to עבדים, avadim, slaves who are in
what way similar to בני שפחות? benei shefachot? מה בני שפחות מלו
ולא טבלו דעושין יין נסך, ma benei shefachot malu velo tavlu de’osin
yein nesech, those בני שפחות benei shefachot who have undergone the מילה
milah circumcision but not gone to the מקווה, mikveh, those are the
ones who can make יין נסך, yein nesech, that is they’re not
fully slave enough to be considered Jewish enough that they don’t make
יין נסך. yein nesech. מלו וטבלו לא, malu vetavlu lo, but if
they underwent both מילה milah and טבילה, tevilah, they no longer make
יין נסך. yein nesech. אף עבדים כן. af avadim ken. So the
same rule should apply to עבדים. avadim. Just like בני שפחות benei
shefachot if they’re only transitional, they haven’t yet fully undergone מילה milah
to become fully considered... Now again, this is even someone who grew
up in the Jewish home, but if he hasn’t had the מילה,
milah, he’s not considered an עבד eved enough to be fully trusted
for יין נסך. yein nesech. So too עבדים מלו וטבלו לא, avadim
malu vetavlu lo, that is if they’ve undergone full conversion to become
עבדים, avadim, then they no longer make יין נסך. yein nesech. אף
עבדים כן. af avadim ken. לאפוקי מדרב נחמן, la’afokei mid’Rav Nachman, and
this uproots or contradicts the position of רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, that
is within רב, Rav, רב Rav must disagree with רב נחמן. Rav
Nachman. אמר שמואל, amar Shmuel, so it’s good for רב Rav to
have a מחלוקת machloket with שמואל. Shmuel. רב נחמן Rav Nachman quoting
שמואל, Shmuel, דאמר רב נחמן אמר שמואל הלוקח עבדים מן העובדי כוכבים,
de’amar Rav Nachman amar Shmuel halokeach avadim min ha’ovedei kochavim,
someone who buys slaves from a non-Jew, אף על פי שמלו וטבלו,
af al pi shemalu vetavlu, even if they’ve undergone מילה milah and
טבילה, tevilah, עושין יין נסך, osin yein nesech, they can make יין
נסך, yein nesech, that is even if they fully underwent the formal
process of conversion to becoming a
slave. Why? עד שתשקע עבודה זרה מפיהם, ad shetishka avodah zarah mipeihem,
that is until they actually fully renounce or stop mentioning the עבודה
זרה, avodah zarah, stop talking about it in any regard. It’s interesting
to think about sometimes when people curse, Jews will often mention
even sarcastically or ironically or unintentionally mention the deities of other religions.
So עד שתשקע עבודה זרה מפיהם, ad shetishka avodah zarah mipeihem, that
you shouldn’t even be mentioning עבודה זרה avodah zarah worship. That is
that even if someone who’s undergone, a slave who’s been bought by
a Jewish master and has undergone the full conversion process to become
a slave, according to שמואל Shmuel and according to רב נחמן, Rav
Nachman, they would need to not only undergo the formal process but
also reach a point where they’ve no longer even thinking of עבודה
זרה avodah zarah anymore, that they’ve internalized what it means to live
in a Jewish household. So that could take several years perhaps. That
is even after they’ve fully undergone the process of conversion to become
a slave, they’re not not trusted regarding יין נסך yein nesech until
they no longer really worship it or believe in it at all.
Yeah.
Just to cap this whole last paragraph, I think what seems like
what happened here is if we read the first version as טמא,
tamei, the implication is that the status of these people who are
מלו ולא טבלו malu velo tavlu is fully non-Jewish, right? So formally
they should create טומאה tumah and they should create יין נסך. yein
nesech. And the חידוש chidush is that the קטנים ketanim don’t have
כוונה kavanah because they’re not familiar. Exactly. And that’s why it supports
רב. Rav. Right. Whereas when we change it to טהור, tahor, it
implies that they’re basically almost Jewish, and the only reason why they
might be able to be אוסר oser something is because they have
that extra עבודה זרה avodah zarah we’re worried about them.
Exactly. Right. And that also reframes how, and this is the debate
throughout the פרק, perek, how much when we’re talking about סתם יינם,
stam yeinam, is it a concern of this person is not Jewish
and I’m distancing myself from non-Jewish wine, or is it this person
is an עובד עבודה זרה oved avodah zarah and I’m distancing myself
from what could potentially be or has a high risk of being
יין נסך? yein nesech?
And so that’s again, this סוגיא sugya opens up a lot of
that thing. Oh, קטנים אין יודעין בטיב עבודה זרה ומשמשיה, ketanim ein
yodein betiv avodah zarah umishamesheha, children don’t know how to worship עבודה
זרה. avodah zarah. So or they grew up in a Jewish home
and so they don’t know or how soon do they forget to
mention the עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. So all of those ingredients lead
this סוגיא sugya to be suggesting more that it’s about how much
is there a risk that this wine is יין נסך yein nesech
and not about a technical problem that the דרבנן de’Rabbanan had just
oh non-Jews handled it. And again, the question of כוונה kavanah is
going to play into that as well.
Well, but you know, if you go up to the tree...
Well exactly, the question of כוונה, kavanah, if I touch it without
כוונה, kavanah, then I couldn’t have made it יין נסך, yein nesech,
real יין נסך, yein nesech, but so how much is the rabbinic
safeguard around the formal rule level. Right. So the formal rule and
the exceptions and how far are we going to extend those parameters,
that’s all what’s being worked out here, which is always what happens
with הלכה, halacha, which is that we have a paradigm and then
we start building it and then we have okay, well what are
the liminal cases that we’re testing? So קמשמע לן דלא. kamashma lan
dela. So that רב Rav disagrees with שמואל Shmuel and therefore the
way רב Rav reads this ברייתא braita has to support his position
and that goes against שמואל. Shmuel. Obviously, I would assume שמואל Shmuel
would have a way to read the ברייתא braita that better fits
his position which is that even if... And even after מלו וטבלו,
malo v'tavlo, they have to renounce עבודה זרה, avoda zara, that שמואל
Shmuel would have a way to read the ברייתא braita as well.
So גופא. gufa. Now, so what did we have? We had a
story about רב Rav and רב Rav defended his position. Then we
had a discussion of, okay, רב's Rav position was challenged by this
ברייתא braita and רב Rav was able to defend himself for this
ברייתא. braita. And then introduced in that discussion of the ברייתא braita
was a position of שמואל Shmuel
who disagrees with רב. Rav. So now we have another גופא. gufa.
We have גופא אמר רב נחמן אמר שמואל הלוקח עבדים מן העובדי
כוכבים אף על פי שמלו וטבלו עושין יין נסך עד שתשקע עבודה
כוכבים מפיהם. gufa amar Rav Nachman amar Shmuel halokeach avadim min ha'ovdei
kochavim af al pi shemalo v'tavlo osin yein nesech ad shetishka avoda
kochavim mipihem. The position of רב נחמן Rav Nachman quoting שמואל, Shmuel,
a person who buys non-Jewish slaves, a slave from a non-Jewish owner,
even though they've undergone מילה mila and טבילה, tvila, that is they've
reached the point of formally having converted to the slave status of
owned by a Jew, עושין יין נסך, osin yein nesech, they still,
their contact makes the wine סתם יינם, stam yeinam, עד שתשקע עבודה
כוכבים מפיהם ad shetishka avoda kochavim mipihem until they stop mentioning or
stop
worshipping idols from their mouths. Wait, weren't they Jews by then?
No, they're slaves, they're עבדים. avadim.
But I mean, but if they're מלו וטבלו, malo v'tavlo, I mean,
but like...
right, מלו וטבלו malo v'tavlo to become עבד כנעני. eved Kena'ani.
But they're חייב במצוות כנשים. chayav b'mitzvot kenashim.
Of course. And שמואל Shmuel is very מחמיר, machmir, he says their
contact with wine we're still, meaning the first week on the job,
right? I just bought this slave, I took him to the מוהל
mohel and he got a מילה, mila, I took him to the
מקוה, mikvah, great, done. He's an עבד, eved, fully חייב chayav in
all of these מצוות. mitzvot. But he still worshipped Zeus in his
free time. Like I didn't, I never brainwashed him enough having him
in my home to know that he lives in a Jewish context
enough, that takes time. So there's a recognition here that someone who
is, especially it's הלוקח עבדים מן העובדי כוכבים. halokeach avadim min ha'ovdei
kochavim. You purchase the slave from a non-Jewish master, non-Jewish owner, that
is they've been living in a house where the worship was עבודה
זרה. avoda zara. So the slave, we hope over time the slave,
right, we had several weeks
ago עבד חבר כחבר, eved chaver k'chaver, an עבד eved who grows
up in the home of a חבר chaver can be trusted with
the level of stringency like a חבר. chaver. So we assume the
עבדים avadim eventually get inculcated and indoctrinated in the mindset of the
home that they're living in, we would hope. But still, that transition
takes some time. The formal designation of עבד כנעני eved Kena'ani can
be undergone relatively quickly. מילה, mila, טבילה, tvila, boom. But in order
to actually eliminate the risk of making יין נסך, yein nesech, that
they're going to worship the עבודה זרה avoda zara in the bathroom
by accident or secretly, we have to actually wait longer.
And because it's forced, I mean, wouldn't you say the same thing
about like a
גר?
ger? It's certainly because it's forced, that is, obviously slavery is about,
you know, the slave has no say in the matter at all.
This person, you know, we don't know whether they're willingly being sold
to a Jew at all. They're being treated like livestock or anything
else. They're being bought and sold between a Jewish owner and a
non-Jewish owner. And so at this point the consideration of יין נסך
yein nesech is, well, this is also a human being who has
a religion and religious beliefs, we have to take into account as
well. So שמואל Shmuel has a perfectly good reason to be מחמיר,
machmir, which is עד שתשקע עבודה זרה מפיהם, ad shetishka avoda zara
mipihem, that until they stop actually referring to it, mentioning it, worshipping
it in that regard. So we're going to see. So the analysis
now of שמואל's Shmuel position: וכמה? v'kama?
So to what extent? How long does that take for them to
stop mentioning עבודה זרה? avoda zara? אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי עד
שנים עשר חודש. Amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi ad shneim asar chodesh.
רבי יהושע בן לוי. Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi. It's interesting that רבי
יהושע בן לוי, Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, who's in ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael more or less contemporaneous with שמואל, Shmuel, is teaching an explanation
of שמואל's Shmuel teachings. Does that mean שמואל Shmuel had gotten it
from already the earliest אמוראים Amoraim in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and
רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi had a divergent or
parallel explanation of the same law? Does it mean שמואל's Shmuel teaching
made it back to ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and רבי יהושע בן
לוי Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi could comment on it there? That's an
interesting question.
You know what's occurring to me, Barry, like you know, this is
a very binary world, right? Everyone's either religious... it just depends to
whom, right? Or what, right?
It was Zeus or God. Everyone is religious, right?
Until the Enlightenment, but you know, but now it's like a very
different reality. A lot of people just like are nothing. I don't
care about Zeus, I don't care about your God, or our God,
or any God. I don't care about anything, you know what I
mean?
So the question of what's the status of an atheist in הלכה
halacha is is a fascinating question. There's not so much material about
it because the whole notion of being atheistic really only developed to
fullest extent, I would say... as Rabbi Linzer was pointing out, right,
the the philosophers are maybe the best point of that, which is
the Greek philosophers in their disputations with the rabbis are always saying,
your God says this, your God says that. They never talk about
their God because the Greek philosophers were very minimally theistic as much
as possible. They didn't really have a structured religion, obviously Plato talks
about it a bit, but there was a sense that these Greek
philosophers, maybe they were אפיקורוס Epicurean or whatever, but they didn't have
such a full notion of a religious practice. But the general people
we're talking about עובדי כוכבים ovdei kochavim are all real idol worshippers.
And nowadays, if you pick a random person off the street, at
least in New York City, well, New York City even maybe is
a bad example because New York City you have plenty of people
who are... deeply religious also. You have a split across America, and
America maybe more than other countries. Say you go to England, something
like seventy percent of people in England are basically not religious in
any regard. So you pick a person off the street in London,
do they have the status of an עובד עבודה זרה oved avodah
zarah in the same way maybe that someone in New York would
or in ancient Rome would?
Is it worth a different shape between that?
I'm not sure. I think it's certainly something that's worth exploring much
more deeply, but again like I said, sort of classical sources don't
have much to say about it. At the end of the day,
our הלכות halachot about סתם יינם stam yeinam certainly
have a rich texture even with dealing with people we know are
עובדי עבודה זרה. ovdei avodah zarah. How much the אשכנזי Ashkenazic tradition
has been tried to be as lenient as possible because of the
realities. Certainly the fact that many of these people don't worship עבודה
זרה avodah zarah at all or are not religious at all maybe
is a great benefit for us. It's actually another reason to be
lenient. Okay, so let's continue here. וכמה אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי?
Vekamah amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi? עד שנים עשר חודש. Ad sneim
asar chodesh. For twelve months. So that's how long living in a
Jewish home for twelve months is enough to get the person to
stop referring to עבודה זרה avodah zarah in any reverential way or
to stop worshipping in it in any serious way. Yeah?
Now I was thinking about the slaves in the South, how they
had such a deep religious connection. Right. Although it was the same
religion as the masters there perhaps, but
nevertheless what I'm saying is, twelve, they held on to that as
their... Right. And you could imagine and Jewish people when we were
slaves also. Right. But the same religion as the masters there perhaps,
but nevertheless what I'm saying is, twelve, they held on to that
as their...
Right. And the question is how much influence can the slave master
exert or whatever. And here, obviously you see שמואל's Shmuel point, and
maybe רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi is actually disagreeing.
שמואל's Shmuel point is עד שתשקע עבודה זרה מפיהם. ad shetishka avodah
zarah mipiehem. Could take decades, could take however long it takes for
this person. רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi wants it
to be a hard and fast rule that can be applied universally.
It makes life easier. It makes life easier, it makes it easier
to assess or to... and again, how much does the slave owner
have a personal relationship with the slave to know oh, what are
your religious practices? Am I bringing you to שול shul with me
or not? All of those questions are very different. You imagine a
family that owns one slave or two slaves and a family that
owns a hundred slaves. It's going to be a very different kind
of dynamic. Generally in the ancient world, I think families only maybe
had one or two slaves. It wasn't so common.
People weren't so rich.
People weren't so rich, but even the wealthiest people did not have
many many many slaves like it was in the American South. That
was really the difference, the main, and that was what was particularly
dehumanizing about American slavery was the scale at which it was applied.
Okay. איתיבי רבא לרב נחמן. Eitivei Rava leRav Nachman. So רבא Rava
challenges רב נחמן. Rav Nachman. So רב נחמן Rav Nachman is the
one who had quoted שמואל's Shmuel position that it's even if they've
fully undergone the technical conversion to become an עבד, eved, we're not,
we don't treat them as that they still make יין נסך yayin
nesech until we actually know for sure they don't worship עבודה זרה
avodah zarah anymore. So רבא Rava says
הלוקח עבדים מן עובדי כוכבים, halokeach avadim min ovdei kochavim, quotes another
ברייתא, braita, one who buys a slave from a non-Jew, שמלו ולא
טבלו, shemalu velo tavlu, they've only undergone מילה milah but not going
to the מקוה, mikveh, וכן בני השפחות שמלו ולא טבלו, vechen benei
hashfachot shemalu velo tavlu, so this is the same ברייתא braita we
had before, and also regarding the בני שפחות, benei hashfachot, children of
slave women who themselves have undergone circumcision but they and their mother
never went to the מקוה, mikveh, רוקן ומדרסן בשוק
טמא,
rukan umidrasan bashuk
tamei, their spit and their מדרס, midras, the chairs they sit on
and things like that in a public place are treated as טמא,
tamei, ואמרי לה טהור, veamrei lah tahor, but there's another version of
the ברייתא braita that says טהור. tahor. יינם, yeinam, and the wine
that they handle, גדולים עושין יין נסך, gedolim osin yayin nesech, קטנים
אינו עושה יין נסך, ketanim eino oseh yayin nesech, the adults make
יין נסך yayin nesech and the children do not. אלו הן גדולים
ואלו הן קטנים, eilu hein gedolim ve-eilu hein ketanim, right, what's why
is the difference between adults and children? גדולים שיודעין בטיב עבודה זרה
ומשמשיה gedolim sheyodein betiv avodah zarah umishamesheha because adults know how to
worship עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, קטנים שאין יודעין בטיב עבודה זרה ומשמשיה
ketanim she-ein yodein betiv avodah zarah umishamesheha and children do not know
how to worship עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. So that was the same
ברייתא braita that was taught before as a challenge to רב Rav
and which רב Rav was able to interpret in support of his
own position. And here רבא Rava is using the same ברייתא braita
now to challenge שמואל's Shmuel position. So we're going to see. So
קתני מיהא. ketani miha. So you could learn from this ברייתא: braita:
מלו ולא טבלו אין, malu velo tavlu in, that is if they've
undergone מילה milah even if not טבילה, tevilah, then yes they do
make יין נסך; yayin nesech; מלו וטבלו לא, malu vetavlu lo, but
if they've undergone both מילה milah and טבילה, tevilah, no, that they
no longer make יין נסך yayin nesech and therefore this ברייתא braita
is proof against שמואל Shmuel because שמואל Shmuel said מלו וטבלו, malu
vetavlu, they still make יין נסך yayin nesech until they renounce their
עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. So תרגמה אבני שפחות. targemah abnei shefachot. So
שמואל Shmuel can interpret that that clause of the ברייתא, braita, that
is that they no longer make יין נסך yayin nesech if they've
undergone מילה milah even if not טבילה, tevilah, that would apply only
to the בני שפחות. benei hashfachot.
Right, who grew up
anyway in a Jewish house. Which is a similar, similar interpretation by
the way to רב. Rav. That is רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel
are both having trouble with this ברייתא braita and they both interpret
the ברייתא braita along similar lines, which is also interesting that the
sort of Babylonian approach to this ברייתא, braita, which is in a
תוספתא Tosefta maybe a more ירושלמי Yerushalmi approach,
there's that divergence there and you can see they interpret it differently
along the same track. Okay, so אבני שפחות. abnei shefachot. וכן קתני
v'chein katani ארוכה ומדרסה, aruka u-midrasah, but then how do you interpret
that according to the הלכה halacha that their spit and their chair
is considered to be טמא? tamei? So הניחא למאן דאמר haniha leman
d'amar טמא, tamei, it makes sense if you say טמא tamei because
that is technically they're still considered non-Jewish and therefore if they they're
treated with the laws of טומאה, tumah, but because they grew up
in the Jewish home we treat them leniently regarding יין נסך. yen
nesech. אלא למאן דאמר ela leman d'amar טהור, tahor, but if you
say that we treat their מדרס midras and their רוק rok as
טהור, tahor, even if it's in רשות הרבים, reshus harabim, and therefore
it sounds like we're treating them sort of at an equivalent level,
sorry, that we're lenient about it even if it's not a ספק,
safek, even if it's a ודאי vadai טומאה, tumah, that is we're
lenient about their
status as non-Jews, so מאי איכא למימר, ma ika lemeimar, how can
we understand this? הא קא משמע לן ha kamashma lan עבדים avadim
דומיא dumya דבני שפחות. devnei shfachos. We must be teaching about not
בני שפחות bnei shfachos themselves, it must be that שמואל Shmuel interprets
it as slaves who are comparable to בני שפחות, bnei shfachos, the
same as רב, Rav, this like you can see it's a duplication
of the same סוגיא sugya almost. So מה בני השפחות גדולים הוא
דעושין יין נסך. ma bnei hashfachos gedolim hu d'osin yen nesech. So
just like the children of these slave women if they're adults they
make יין נסך, yen nesech, קטנים אין עושין יין נסך, ktanim ein
osin yen nesech, the children don't because the children still are uneducated
in the ways of עבודה זרה. Avoda Zara. אף עבדים נמי, af
avadim nami, so the slaves themselves, that is who were purchased, גדולים
עושין יין נסך, gedolim osin yen nesech, קטנים אין עושין יין נסך,
ktanim ein osin yen nesech, and so adults make יין נסך yen
nesech but not the children. לאפוקי מדרב, l'afokei mide-Rav, and this is
in support of שמואל Shmuel's position against רב Rav's position, דאמר רב
תינוק בן יומו עושה יין נסך. d'amar Rav tinok ben yomo oseh
yen nesech. So it's very interesting at the end of the day
because they've both been pressed against a wall by this ברייתא, baraita,
it ends up that רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel's position in fact
are not such a disagreement, they're actually very close, but that שמואל
Shmuel thinks רב Rav is an extremist about children, that רב Rav
thinks even a קטן, katan, קטן בן יומו עושה יין נסך, katan
ben yomo oseh yen nesech, which רב Rav holds, but he holds
it only under very limited circumstances, which שמואל Shmuel would actually maybe
somewhat agree to. And רב Rav interprets שמואל Shmuel's position very extreme,
that he considers the significance of renouncing עבודה זרה Avoda Zara even
if מלו וטבלו, malu v'tavlu, and שמואל Shmuel when pressed against the
wall with this ברייתא baraita actually has to come back to the
middle. So in the end the מחלוקת machlokes started off very big
and because they've both been contradicted by this ברייתא baraita we actually
end up that רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel's position are relatively close
together. It seems the main disagreement is about קטנים. ktanim. רב Rav
thinks a קטן katan does make יין נסך yen nesech and שמואל
Shmuel thinks not.
So has רב Rav been disproven then?
רב Rav's case has been limited specifically to a קטן katan who
is being bought as a slave not who grew up with a
slave mother in a Jewish home, and
right, so that's the case that they're debating. שמואל Shmuel thinks no,
a קטן katan doesn't count for יין נסך yen nesech and רב
Rav thinks that they do. רב Rav thinks so. רב Rav thinks
that they do, sorry, I switched, שמואל Shmuel says no, רב Rav
says yes. Okay. הא קא משמע לן עבדים דומיא דבני שפחות גדולים
עושין יין נסך קטנים אין עושין יין נסך, ha kamashma lan avadim
dumya d'vnei shfachos gedolim osin yen nesech ktanim ein osin yen nesech,
אף עבדים נמי גדולים עושין יין נסך קטנים אין עושין יין נסך,
af avadim nami gedolim osin yen nesech ktanim ein osin yen nesech,
לאפוקי מדרב דאמר רב תינוק בן יומו עושה יין נסך, l'afokei mide-Rav
d'amar Rav tinok ben yomo oseh yen nesech, קא משמע לן דלא.
ka mashma lan d'lo. And therefore this ברייתא baraita according to how
שמואל Shmuel interprets it is the best proof against רב, Rav, and
the same ברייתא baraita as interpreted by רב Rav is the best
proof against שמואל. Shmuel. So really they're just disagreeing about how do
you what specific detail of בני שפחות bnei shfachos do you apply
parallel to עבדים avadim in order to determine the הלכה halacha about
children,
which children do or do not make יין נסך yen nesech
based on the word וכן. v'chein.
וכן, v'chein, right, because there's an equivalence in the ברייתא baraita between
וכן עבדים. v'chein avadim. It starts off בני השפחות bnei hashfachos and
then וכן עבדים, v'chein avadim, right.
Okay, so now that was all that we had a story about
רב Rav and the detail there, we had גופא Gufa dealing with
רב Rav's position, שמואל Shmuel's position was brought up as a tangent,
then we had גופא Gufa dealing with שמואל Shmuel's position where רב
Rav was brought up and that was the end of this סוגיא
sugya and now another case. ההוא עובדא, hahu uvda, another case, דהוה
במחוזא, d'hava b'Mahoza,
it was in the city of מחוזא. Mahoza. אתא עובד כוכבים, ata
oveid kochavim, עייל לחנותא דישראל, aya l'chanusa d'Yisrael, and he went into
the Jewish store. We'll see how far we can go, the problem
is this סוגיא sugya then goes into the next part, but we
have a little bit more time, so we'll see. Okay. ההוא עובדא
דהוה במחוזא אתא עובד כוכבים עייל לחנותא דישראל. hahu uvda d'hava b'Mahoza
ata oveid kochavim aya l'chanusa d'Yisrael. אמר להו, amar lehu, he said
to him, okay, אית לכו חמרא לזבוני, is l'chu chamra l'zavuni, do
you have a wine for sale? אמר ליה, amar lei, so לא,
lo, he says I don't have any wine for sale. He went
into like Skyview Wines, no wines? Right, exactly.
So הוה יתיב חמרא בדאוולא, hava yasiv chamra b'davala, but there
was wine sitting there in a bucket, like דולא dola like to
draw the water,
so שדי ביה ידיה, shadi bei yadei, he put his hand into
it, שכשך ביה, shichshach bei, and he shook it around. אמר להו,
amar lehu, האי לאו חמרא הוא, hai lav chamra hu, he said
oh that's not wine. No, he's saying oh is this is this
not wine? Is this not wine? Right. So שקליה, shaklei, so then
he he took it, that is he basically he let him buy
it but the Jewish merchant... was very upset.
So
it
sounds like again the Jewish merchant is allowed to sell. Whatever it
says here, שקליה האיך ברתחיה שדייה לדנא. shaklei haich beritchei shadye ledana.
That's the end of it. The other thing is that the Jewish
store owner then took this stuff that
this non-Jewish person touched and then
threw it into a barrel of wine. That's how they're explaining it.
Right. שקליה האיך shaklei haich what? שקליה האיך shaklei haich that one,
okay.
ברתחיה beritchei when he was angry. He was angry that the non-Jew
touched it.
Yeah. ושדיה לדנא, veshadye ledana, fine. He poured it, okay, he poured
it into a whole barrel of, I see how you're saying. So
the dilution question, sorry, I ended too soon. Okay. ברתחיה שדיה לדנא,
beritchei
shadye
ledana, he pours it into the barrel, שרייה רבא לזבוניה לעובדי כוכבים.
sharaye Rava lezavunei le'ovdei chochavim. And Rava allowed him to sell it
to a non-Jew. So that is what happened. A small amount of
wine became again סתם יינם stam yeinam and then was poured in
intentionally by a Jew into a barrel of kosher wine. And now
the question is what is it בטל batel basically. So according to
Rava, the whatever סתם יינם stam yeinam was created in the jar
will be בטל batel in the whole barrel. It will be nullified,
seemingly. The question is why? Don't we have the rabbinic rule אין
מבטלין איסור לכתחילה? ein mevatlin issur lechatchila? You're not allowed to intentionally
nullify. I don't think he made it an איסור. issur. So maybe
he didn't want to intentionally, he was just upset. ברתחיה, beritchei, he
was upset. So he did it without thinking, he did it without
planning to be בטל, batel, he was just upset about it. Or
maybe we don't apply that rule to an איסור דרבנן issur de-rabbanan
or we don't apply it in this kind of a case, so
at least to the extent that the full barrel where it is
mixed in is permissible to sell, right?
Rava does not say it's permissible to drink it.
So we're seeing the same distinction we saw earlier, which is we
could read it two different ways. Either סתם יינם stam yeinam in
general is permissible to derive benefit from and
it's not בטל, batel, it's just
you can get you can sell סתם יינם. stam yeinam. Or alternatively,
it's prohibited to sell סתם יינם, stam yeinam, but in this case
because it's בתערובת, beta'arovet, it's in a mixture, it's been diluted, that's
why it's allowed, but generally it would not be allowed. Okay, so
those are two different ways to read Rava's פסק. psak. Okay. לזבוניה
לעובדי כוכבים. Lezavunei le'ovdei chochavim. So איפליגו רב הונא בר חיננא ורב
הונא בריה דרב נחמן,
Ipligu Rav Huna bar Chinana veRav Huna brei
deRav Nachman, two other rabbis disagree with him. And as you see,
it's the same structure as the סוגיא sugya we had before. So
these two rabbis disagree with him. They say נפיק שיפורי דרבא ושרו
ונפיק שיפורי דרב הונא בר חיננא ורב הונא בריה דרב נחמן ואסרי.
Nafik shipurei deRava vesharu venafik shipurei deRav Huna bar Chinana veRav Huna
brei deRav Nachman ve'asrei. And so Rava sends out his students to
make a proclamation that it's permissible. And we saw this previously about
the חילק, achilak, the fish fish sauce a few weeks ago as
well. There was a similar case where Rava was lenient and רב
הונא Rav Huna was מחמיר machmir and they had the boat was
docked in the port and they had to, so Rava was like
asserting his authority, he sends out his students, they said it's permissible.
נפיק שיפורי דרב הונא בר חיננא ורב הונא בריה דרב נחמן Nafki
shipurei deRav Huna bar Chinana veRav Huna brei deRav Nachman and these
other two rabbis send out their students ואסרי ve'asrei and they declare
that it's prohibited. So איקלע רב הונא בריה דרב נחמן למחוזא. Iklah
Rav Huna brei deRav Nachman leMechoza. So רב הונא בריה דרב נחמן
Rav Huna brei deRav Nachman finally comes to מחוזא. Mechoza. And he's
the one who said it was אסור. assur. And he's the one
who says it's אסור assur and Rava is in charge in מחוזא
Mechoza and says it's מותר. muttar. So אמר ליה רבא לרב אליקים
שמעיה. Amar lei Rava leRav Elyakim shamayei. So Rava says to... He
said it was מותר. muttar. Right, Rava said it's מותר muttar tells
רב אליקים Rav Elyakim his assistant, his teaching assistant, תרוק תרוק גלי
דלא לינתנו אינשי לנטרוד... Tarok tarok gale dlo lintenu inshei lenatrud... so
basically like go suppress his, right? תרוק גלי, Tarok gale, close the
door to keep him out, so because he's going that is keep
him out of מחוזא Mechoza basically because tell the city guards to
keep him out or something because דלא לינתנו אינשי לנטרוד... dlo lintenu
inshei lenatrud... he's going to cause a lot of problems for people
because this guy is a big מחמיר machmir basically. Okay. על לגביה,
Al legabeih, but he came anyway to visit to visit Rava. So
now we have רב הונא בריה דרב נחמן Rav Huna brei deRav
Nachman visiting Rava in מחוזא. Mechoza. Okay. על לגביה אמר ליה כי
האי גוונא מאי. Al legabeih amar lei ki hai gavna mai. So
why did you permit this case of the wine that was diluted
in the other one? So אמר ליה אסורה אפילו בהנאה. Amar lei
asura afilu behana'ah. He said it should be prohibited even even in
even בהנאה. behana'ah. והא מר הוא דאמר שכשך אין עושין יין נסך?
Veha mar hu de'amar shichshech ein osin yayin nesech? But didn't you,
that is didn't you Rava say that if you stick you just
shake it around, that is you didn't pour the bottle or something
like that, it does not create the status of יין נסך? yayin
nesech? אימא דאמרי אנא לבר מדמי דההוא חמרא, Eima de'amri ana levar
midamei dehau hamra, except for the case of similar to that wine.
No, no, no, מדמי midamei as in like the money of that...
In other words, yeah, you could sell it to a guy except
for the value of that wine. That is, the dilution. So if
it was one... sorry, okay. דאמרי אנא לבר מדמי דההוא חמרא. de'amri
ana levar midamei dehau hamra. So the reason why, so I said
oh when I said all the way back on... It doesn't sound
like he said, right? It doesn't sound like that. The way the
teaching... The way the teaching was transmitted or was reported, and certainly
the way his students acted, sounds like it should have been that
he that he was very lenient. But here רבא Rava under pressure
maybe of רב הונא בר רב נחמן בריה דרב נחמן Rav Huna
bar Rav Nachman Brei deRav Nachman visiting him in person, so where
was the broken telephone? Was רבא'ס Rava's פסק psak reported overly leniently
actually in מחוזא Mechoza or is it that רבא Rava now under
pressure is backing off a little bit when challenged by one of
his colleagues? We can relate to that sometimes when some liberal rabbi
comes out with it and they say oh it's great and then
it's like oh no no no no no details right. Right, oh
I didn't really mean it, right? I have many examples of things
like that. Twice not three times. Right, exactly. So מי אמר. mi
amar. Okay, so did I ever say דמי לההוא חמרא, damei lehahu
hamra, right, that line, דמי דההוא חמרא מי אמרי? damei dehahu hamra
mi amri? So אמר רבא כי אתאי לפומבדיתא, amar Rava ki atai
lePumbedita, when I came to visit פומבדיתא, Pumbedita, אכפיה נחמני שמעתא ומתניתא
דאסיר. akfay Nachmani shmateta umatnita de-asir. So נחמני, Nachmani, נחמני Nachmani is
אביי. Abaye. So רבא Rava calls אביי Abaye נחמני. Nachmani. So when
I went to פומבדיתא, Pumbedita, so אביי Abaye challenged me with שמעתא,
shmateta, with this teaching, ומתניתא umatnita and with a משנה mishna דאסיר,
de-asir, that it should be prohibited, that the whole wine should be
prohibited, not just to sell it proportionally to the amount of the
cost of how much was the kosher wine, how much was not.
So שמעתא דההוא עובדא דהוה בנהרדעא. shmateta dehahu uvda de-hava be-Nahardea. Let's
stop here because this is going to be the next part of
the סוגיא. sugya. So I'll leave that for Rabbi Linzer to teach
tomorrow. Hope everyone has a great day. Thank you very much, and
sorry about the end of it, obviously didn't prepare.